Edmund Liszka Collection CPAA 88.05
Connecticut Polish American Archives
Edmund Liszka Collection
1938-2005
CPAA 88.05
Connecticut Polish American Archives
1.5 Linear feet
Mr. Edmund Liszka was very active in the Hartford's Polonia after WWII. He owned a travel agency, hosted a radio program and later on a TV program. He sponsored and organized many cultural events related to Poland and Polish history, including bringing artists form Poland. He documented various events with professional photographs and donated them to the archives. Mr. Liszka was recognized for his activism within Polonia with many awards and medals.
Liszka, Edmund
Biographical/Historical note
Mr. Edmund Liszka, owner of The Liszka Travel Agency in Hartford, CT donated his papers and photographs in 1988 to the Connecticut Polish American Archives. Mr. Liszka was born in New Hampshire, he moved back to Poland where he received further education. He returned to Hartford shortly before WWII and become active in the Polish community. He has hosted the Polish Radio program since 1938 and in 1980’s he started television program on Channel 13 in Hartford. He was an impresario and organized many concerts and performances of various Polish groups (including Mazowsze) and screening of Polish films. The collection contains a series of photographs of Hartford Polonia and its activities, books, and materials related to the Connecticut celebration of the Millennium of Polish Christianity in 1966. Mr. Liszka was a member of the committee. Mr. Liszka was awarded post humusly the Cross of Merit of the Republic of Poland by the Consul General during the Polish Day at the Capitol on May 2, 2006. Edmund Liszka died on April 29, 2006 after long illness.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Custodial History note
Material in this collection was donated by Mr. Edmund Liszka in 1988.
Scope and Contents note
This collection has material related to history of local Connecticut Polonia. It contains anniversary publications, photographs and pamhlets from local organizations.
Catholics, Polish--United States; Ethnic radio broadcasting--United States; Pamphlets.; Photographs; Polish American Congress; Polish Americans--Connecticut--Biography; Polish people -- United States; Radio broadcasting, Polish--United States
- Bulletin Edmund Liszka Travel Agency, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- United Polish Society, Awards dinners and events; diploma of recognition for Mr. Liszka, 1949-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Mr. Edmund Liszka award and recognition during Polish Day at the Capital, May 2nd, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Mr. Edmund Liszka obituary, April 29, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Liszka, Edmund: wartime ration booklet, telegram on refugee relief, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Millennium of Poland's Christianity - memorabilia, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Millennium of Poland's Christianity - 2 programs: Artistic program and military ball 1-15-66, Concert of Polish music and song, 12-4-66, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bronze plaque commemorating the Millennium of Poland's Christianity, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- State and city Proclamations: Polish Constitution Day 1940; Walter Maznicki Day, 1976; Katyn Memorial Day 1977, 1940-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Najwiekszy Zbior Piosenek Polskich," compilation of Polish songs by Edmund Liszka, New Britain, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Financial Statements: Polish National Home 1975, 1986; Polish American Congress 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Polskie Programy Radiowe w Stanach Zjednoczonych," by Jozef Migala, Warszawa: Wydawnictwa Radia i Telewizji with a chapter about Edmund Liszka, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Clippings on various Polish events in Connecticut(Polish language), 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Polish-American Congress, CT. - Program of 62nd Anniversary of Polish Independence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- PNA, Hartford - List of Presidents (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "Crazy Horse and Korczak," by Robb DeWall; Crazy Horse, South Dakota,1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Golden Jubilee Souvenir brochure, Nest 88 Polish Falcons of New Britain, May 18, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- 25th National Convention & 20th Field Meet of the Polish Falcons of America, New Britain, CT, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- 50th Anniversary of St. Stanislaus Kostka Church, Waterbury, CT, May 5, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Material separated - Polish-American Aniversary booklets (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Cultural programs flyers 1960's and 1970's (Box 1, Folder 21)
- XXV Lecie Choru Polonia Paderewski, 1952-1977 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- 15 Lecie Osrodka Harcerskiego New Britain-Hartford, CT, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- General Casimir Pulaski Memorial Monument, Mass and Dedication pamphlet, July 3rd, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- 75 years Church and People, Holy Name Church, Stamford, CT, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Bal Menuet Program, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Msgr. Stanislaw Musiel - photograph (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Rev. Bombolinski for the WKNB-TV program - photo (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Vice President Richard Nixon visiting Hartford and Polish National Home (photos 2), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Cardinal Karol Wojtyla visitng New Britain, photograph, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Judge Walter Sidor of Hartford - photo (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Kazimierz Wierzynski visiting Hartford - 4 photos (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Gen. Tadeusz Bor-Komorowski visiting Hartford with Joseph Kozielewicz, President of PAC Conn. District (photograph), 1954 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- General Wladyslaw Anders visits Hartford (photos 5) and clippings (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Tomasz Arciszewski, former Prime Minister of the Polish Government in Exile visits Hartford (photograph), 1950 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Polish artist Loda Halama performs in the Bushnell Auditorium, Hartford, CT (photograph), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Polish writer Melchior Wankowicz visits Hartford, CT (photos 3) (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Polish Soccer Club "Ogniwo" from Hartford, Ct (photographs), 1950's (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Edmund Liszka - Photographs from various Polonia events (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Photographs from Pulaski Day Parade in Hartford, CT, 1950's (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Photographs from Pulaski Day Parade in Hartford [n.d.] includes local politicians and veterans, etc. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Photographs from Pulaski Day Parade in Hartford mounted (6 photos), 1959 (Box 3, Folder 5)